<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>1 on Justin Sybrandt</title>
    <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication_types/1/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 1 on Justin Sybrandt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Justin Sybrandt</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://sybrandt.com/publication_types/1/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Are Abstracts Enough for Hypothesis Generation?</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/are-abstracts-enough-for-hg/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/are-abstracts-enough-for-hg/</guid>
      <description>We explore the effect corpus size and document length have on knowledge network-based HG systems, primarily by comparing their performance with full-text papers against abstracts. Our experimental studies are based on the HG system Moliere that extends the basic principals of knowledge discovery networks introduced in earlier works. This centers around two major studies: the first comparing the performance of our system trained on abstract and full-text versions of the same document set, the second comparing the performance of iterative halves of a large abstract set.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Validation of Hypothesis Generation Systems via Candidate Ranking</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/validation-and-topic-driven-ranking/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 22 Aug 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/validation-and-topic-driven-ranking/</guid>
      <description>In this paper we propose novel hypothesis ranking methods and a method to validate HG systems that does not require expert input and allows for large validation sets. This method judges a system by its ability to rank hypotheses by plausibility, similarly to how a human scientist must rank potential research directions during candidate selection. We start by dividing a corpus based on a ``cut date,&amp;rdquo; and provide a system only information that was priorly available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MOLIERE: Automatic Biomedical Hypothesis Generation System</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/moliere-automatic-biomedical-hypothesis-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/moliere-automatic-biomedical-hypothesis-generation/</guid>
      <description>MOLIERE is a hypothesis generation system which is able to identify potential relationships from large text corpora. Our presented system was trained on the MEDLINE dataset, containing nearly 25 million documents dating back to the late 1800&amp;rsquo;s. We validate our system by predicting recent findings using only information present before 2010. These validations efforts are confirmed with the help of a domain expert.
Watch our promotional video or our KDD talk.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>