<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Opinion on Justin Sybrandt</title>
    <link>http://sybrandt.com/tags/opinion/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Opinion on Justin Sybrandt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Justin Sybrandt</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 May 2018 14:18:52 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://sybrandt.com/tags/opinion/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Activism on the Path to Data Justice</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/post/data-bias-18-5-20/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 May 2018 14:18:52 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/post/data-bias-18-5-20/</guid>
      <description>&lt;!--
Thesis:
  Both scientists and citizens should organize around representative data.
Outline:
   
--&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I had the opportunity to attend a lecture from a prominent scientist at a high-profile national lab.
In this talk he touched on recent work wherein his team simulated the effects of a nuclear detonation in a large urban area.
He found the data-driven aspects &amp;mdash; such as the combination of satellite images and census data &amp;mdash; to be particularly interesting, and explained how his simulated catastrophe scenarios might inform policy decisions.
After all, he explained, we ought to have a plan to evacuate highly populated, dense cities if need be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I asked him about bias in his data sources, he deflected.
I was concerned for groups that are typically underrepresented by the census&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:1&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:1&#34;&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, particularly in urban areas&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:2&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:2&#34;&gt;2&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;.
I though a policy maker may see these simulation results, presented by a prominent scientist at a high-profile national lab, and make a decision about evacuation policy that was biased against these groups.
After all, this policy maker may not understand the inequalities baked into data-driven models &amp;mdash; especially those using the census.
The scientist&amp;rsquo;s replied saying his simulation was still preliminary and no policy maker has seen it yet.
Still, seemed as if problems around biased data had not been discussed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I believe this conversation is not unique &amp;mdash; despite rising concern within the machine learning community, those outside the field are just coming around to biased data sets.
And while some recent public-facing works address this issue&lt;sup class=&#34;footnote-ref&#34; id=&#34;fnref:3&#34;&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;#fn:3&#34;&gt;3&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt;, I don&amp;rsquo;t think common citizens have a clue as to how their data is used.
Yet technology grows in potential as it entangles around data, and the future holds many challenges that call for more powerful technology.
So with no alternative, we must ensure that everyone knows the importance of representative data.
We ought to elevate datasets &amp;mdash; like the census &amp;mdash; in the public conscience and hold them to a higher standard.
Otherwise, as I am not the first to point out, we will find ourselves with policy adapted to those surveyed rather than those effected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>