<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>0 on Justin Sybrandt</title>
    <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication_types/0/</link>
    <description>Recent content in 0 on Justin Sybrandt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019 Justin Sybrandt</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://sybrandt.com/publication_types/0/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Inhibition of the DDX3 prevents HIV-1 Tat and cocaine-induced neurotoxicity by targeting microglia activation</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/2019-inhibition-of-the-ddx3-prevents-hiv-1-tat-and-cocaine-induced-neurotoxicity-by-targeting-microglia-activation/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/2019-inhibition-of-the-ddx3-prevents-hiv-1-tat-and-cocaine-induced-neurotoxicity-by-targeting-microglia-activation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Drive-by Health Monitoring to Detect Bridge Damage Considering Environmental and Operational Effects</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/2018-drive-by-health-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/2018-drive-by-health-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>Drive-by Health Monitoring utilizes accelerometers mounted on commercial and civilian vehicles to gather dynamic response data that can be used to continuously evaluate the health of bridges faster and with less equipment than traditional structural health monitoring practices. Because vehicles and bridges create a coupled system, vehicle acceleration data contains information about bridge frequencies that can be used as health indicators. However, for drive-by health monitoring to be viable, variabilities in dynamic measurements caused by environmental and operational parameters, such as temperature, vehicle speed, traffic, and surface roughness need to be considered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To Agile or Not to Agile: A Comparison of Software Development Methodologies</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/to-agile-or-not-to-agile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/to-agile-or-not-to-agile/</guid>
      <description>During the graduate course on software development methods, Ruslan Shaydulin and I put together a paper analyzing different software methodologies. We find, through our literature review, that the landscape of methodologies has changed rapidly within the last decade. Additionally, we find a large number of pros and cons for all methodologies.
These strengths and weaknesses are detailed in the associated work. Note, this work is unpublished.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hypergraph Partitioning Data</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/2019-hypergraph-partitioning/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/2019-hypergraph-partitioning/</guid>
      <description>#matrix_content { } .large_img { zoom:.25; } .btn-group { margin:auto; display: flex; flex-direction: row; justify-content: center; margin-bottom: 10pt; } .btn-group button { background-color: #4CAF50; /* Green background */ border: 1px solid green; /* Green border */ color: white; /* White text */ padding: 10px 24px; /* Some padding */ cursor: pointer; /* Pointer/hand icon */ float: left; /* Float the buttons side by side */ } /* Clear floats (clearfix hack) */ .</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>