<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Publications on Justin Sybrandt</title>
    <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Publications on Justin Sybrandt</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2017 Justin Sybrandt</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="http://sybrandt.com/publication/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Using Drive-by Health Monitoring to Detect Bridge Damage Considering Environmental and Operational Effects</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/2018-drive-by-health-monitoring/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 12 Nov 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/2018-drive-by-health-monitoring/</guid>
      <description>Drive-by Health Monitoring utilizes accelerometers mounted on commercial and civilian vehicles to gather dynamic response data that can be used to continuously evaluate the health of bridges faster and with less equipment than traditional structural health monitoring practices. Because vehicles and bridges create a coupled system, vehicle acceleration data contains information about bridge frequencies that can be used as health indicators. However, for drive-by health monitoring to be viable, variabilities in dynamic measurements caused by environmental and operational parameters, such as temperature, vehicle speed, traffic, and surface roughness need to be considered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Are Abstracts Enough for Hypothesis Generation?</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/are-abstracts-enough-for-hg/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/are-abstracts-enough-for-hg/</guid>
      <description>Our goal in this paper is to understand the effect data quality has on our hypothesis generation system, Moliere. We train multiple instances of our system and apply our validation techniques to numerically quantify performance differences.
Our different datasets come from Medline and PubMed Central. This required a fair amount cleaning and random sampling, so those wishing to replicate our findings are encouraged to start with the pre-trained datasets. These datasets are preconstructed using data that predates 2010.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Large-Scale Validation of Hypothesis Generation Systems via Candidate Ranking</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/validation-and-topic-driven-ranking/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 18 Oct 2018 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/validation-and-topic-driven-ranking/</guid>
      <description>We explore and implement a number of validation methods in this work. In order to run these for yourself, first setup the Moliere project from our github page. A fair warning, you will need some pretty powerful compute resources. Feel free to reach out or file a github issue for help on that front.
Because the Moliere project represents a significant portion the lead authors thesis work, this codebase is subject to change.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>MOLIERE: Automatic Biomedical Hypothesis Generation System</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/moliere-automatic-biomedical-hypothesis-generation/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 13 Aug 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/moliere-automatic-biomedical-hypothesis-generation/</guid>
      <description>MOLIERE is a hypothesis generation system which is able to identify potential relationships from large text corpora. Our presented system was trained on the MEDLINE dataset, containing nearly 25 million documents dating back to the late 1800&amp;rsquo;s. We validate our system by predicting recent findings using only information present before 2010. These validations efforts are confirmed with the help of a domain expert.
Watch our promotional video or our KDD talk.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>To Agile or Not to Agile: A Comparison of Software Development Methodologies</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/to-agile-or-not-to-agile/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 01 Apr 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/to-agile-or-not-to-agile/</guid>
      <description>During the graduate course on software development methods, Ruslan Shaydulin and I put together a paper analyzing different software methodologies. We find, through our literature review, that the landscape of methodologies has changed rapidly within the last decade. Additionally, we find a large number of pros and cons for all methodologies.
These strengths and weaknesses are detailed in the associated work. Note, this work is unpublished.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Rapid Replication of Multi-Petabyte File Systems</title>
      <link>http://sybrandt.com/publication/rapid-replication-of-multipetabyte-filesystems/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 16 Nov 2015 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://sybrandt.com/publication/rapid-replication-of-multipetabyte-filesystems/</guid>
      <description>DistSync was presented as a Work in Progress (WIP) at the Parallel Data Storage Workshop, as well as in the SC&amp;rsquo;15 poster session. This work was done along with the storage systems group at the National Energy Research Scientific Computing Center (NERSC).
We developed distsync in order to facilitate the move from the Oakland Scientific Facility into a new building at the LBNL Berkeley campus. As part of this process, the scratch file system at the old location needed to be syncronized with an out of date replica present at the new location.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>